# **MUHAMMAD SAIM**

• 35302-8323496-3 • +92-332-4623231 • saimjee53@yahoo.com • Age: 25



Highly analytical and creative Mechanical Instructor with 2 years' experience of teaching a wide variety of mechanical courses, also a project supervisor of final year students and managing routine assignment of Engineering Cell. Also have experience of working with international manufacturing company (SIEMNS) as a design engineer.

### Education

UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY LAHORE (CGPA: 3.76) Lahore, Pakistan Bachelors of Science in Mechanical Engineering and Technology 2012-2016

PUNJAB BOARD OF TECHANIAL EDUCATION LAHORE (82 %)

Lahore, Pakistan 2009-2012

Diploma of Associate Engineering in Mechanical Technology

**BOARD OF INTERMEDIATE AND SECONDARY EDUCATION (86 %)**Secondary School Certificate in Science Group

Lahore, Pakistan 2007-2009

# Experience

#### UNIVERSITY OF OKARA

Okara, Pakistan

# **Assistant IT Cell & Engineering Cell** (July 2016 - Present)

- Managing routine assignment related to engineering works.
- Maintaining University workload and annual budget of teaching and non-teaching staff
- Developing, implementing and evaluating the programs of University Model School.
- Creating a climate hospitable to education.
- Managing school data and maintain a system of controls over accounting transactions.
- Ensure that accounts receivable are collected promptly.

## GOVERNMENT COLLEGE OF TECHNOLOGY SAHIWAL

Sahiwal, Pakistan

**Visiting Instructor** (Sept. 2016 – Present)

- Teaching courses of thermodynamics, machine design, heat transfer, engineering drawing, Auto CAD and CNC Machines.
- Provided training in critical reading, facilitated the process of composing academic forms of writing within various modes and genres, and aided students in computer literacy, oral presentation skills, and MLA formatting.
- Successfully balanced student work-load with teaching work-load
- Improved student participation in the classroom through integration of creative roleplaying exercises and peer review sessions.

- Collaborated with a team of faculty at weekly meeting and actively contributed new ideas on teaching.
- Consistently received positive teacher evaluations from students.
- Demonstrated advanced skills in operating equipment and machines including CNC machines, cutting machines and hydraulic presses.
- Guide and trained the students about CAD/CAM Software, Auto-CAD, MS-Word and MS-PowerPoint.
- Worked with an average of 60 students per class.
- Participate in ongoing staff training sessions.

# KOT ADDU POWER COMPANY Ltd. (KAPCO)

Kot Addu, Pakistan

KAPCO is the Pakistan's first thermal power plant and Asia's second largest power company. KAPCO is a 1600 MW multi fuel and diversified combined cycle power plant with five independent combine cycle power modules including 10 Gas Turbines.

# Industrial Training: (Jan. 2016 – July 2016)

- Design shell and tube type heat exchanger which used to maintain the temperature of the gas turbine lube oil system.
- Working on low emission combustion technology.
- Worked with a team in which they utilize the ash of the power plant.
- Inspection of Blades: Detailed study of Non Destructive Testing of turbine blades and completely understand the method of Die Penetration Test and Magnetic Particle Impression.

### **Academic Activities**

### SEMESTER PROJECT

- "Design and fabrication of a model for energy generation by water wheel" (Jan, 2015 to June, 2015)
  - Objective of this project to get maximum rpm with small head by utilize momentum of the water wheel.
- "Study, Development and Implementation of Environmental Control System for Poultry Farms" (2014)
  - Theme of this project is to design such a system that would sense and control three parameters temperature, humidity and light intensity in an environment.

- **Event Organizer** (2013-2016)
  - Leadership and Development: Managing over 30 executive members, 4 technical forums and a creative hub with 15 members. Introduced the culture of family which developed the sense of ownership among members and executives of the society.

#### Honors and Awards

- Secured 1st position in 4 year university education (2012-2016)
- Recommended by the chairman of the department for event organizer SPDC (2014)
- Participated NUQTA event in PIEAS Islamabad (2014)
- Secured 1st position district level in DAE Mechanical (2012)

# Additional

- Professional Affiliation: International member of ASME (2012-Present)
- Soft Skills: Good with these software's (Auto cad, MS Power, MS Excel, MS Word, Photoshop, coral Draw, CAD/CAM (Boxford TLC-160)
- Interests: Organizing Events, Attending TEDx talks
- Extracurricular activities: Cricket, Badminton, Football

## References:

1) Dr. Khalid Saleem

**Incharge Faculty of Education** (University of Okara)

Email ID: Khalid.saleem@gmail.com, Mobile No: 0301-4400504

2) Mr. Inam Ul Haq

Assistant Professor, Incharge IT-Cell (University of Okara)

Email ID: inam.haq@ue.edu.pk, Mobile No: 0307-7777369

3) Dr. Shahid Imran

**HOD Mechanical Department** (UET KSK Campus)

Email ID: s.imran@uet.edu.pk, Mobile No: 0345-0789829

4) Engr. Gulam Rasul Sabir

Incharge Mechanical Maintenance (Kot Addu Power Company Ltd.)

5) Mr. Muhammad Hafeez

**HOD Mechanical Department** (GCT Sahiwal)

Email ID: hafeezgctswl@gmail.com, Mobile No: 0321-6931933